在这个视频中我将教会你 Kotlin 编程语言的基础
in this video i'll teach you the core of
the Kotlin programming language
Kotlin 是一种这几年很流行的通用的静态类型语言
Kotlin is a general purpose statically
typed language that has become extremely
Kotlin 是一种这几年很流行的通用的静态类型语言
popular in the last few years
Kotlin 既可以用在客户端上
Kotlin can be used on both the client
也可以用在服务端上，这意味着用 Kotlin 写的代码
and the server which means the code can
既可以运行在用户的设备（客户端）上
be run either on the user's device
也可以运行在云服务器（服务端）上
the client or on some computer in the
也可以运行在云服务器（服务端）上用以回应客户端的请求
cloud called the server
which responds to requests from the
也可以运行在云服务器（服务端）上用以回应客户端的请求
client
在客户端方面，Kotlin 现在被广泛应用于安卓开发
on the client kotlin is now widely used
for android development
——为 25 亿台运行安卓操作系统的设备编写应用程序
to write apps for the 2.5 billion
devices running the android operating
——为 25 亿运行安卓操作系统的设备编写应用程序
system
近几年 Kotlin 的受欢迎度大幅上升
kotlin has seen a huge rise in
近几年 Kotlin 的受欢迎度年大幅上升
popularity
我能保证未来的几年中它只会变得更受欢迎
and i can promise you it will only
become more popular in the years to come
Kotlin 是一种编程语言，是我们与计算机交流的一种方式
kotlin is an example of a programming
language which is a way for me and you
Kotlin 是一种编程语言，是我们与计算机交流的一种方式
to communicate with computers
归根结底，计算机只能理解二进制的数字——也就是0和1
at the end of the day computers only
understand binary zeros and ones
所以这些年我们创造了很多种
so over the years we've created many
不同的方法来告诉计算机
different ways to instruct the computer
我们希望它做什么，每一种方法
what we'd like it to do each of these
都被称为一种编程语言
approaches is called a programming
language
你可能已经听说过他们中的一些
and you've probably heard of some of them
例如 C 语言、Java 和 JavaScript
such as c or java or javascript
因为 Kotlin 诞生得更晚，它从早期的编程语言中汲取了教训
since kotlin was created much more recently
it has taken the lessons from
因为 Kotlin 诞生得更晚，它从早期的编程语言中汲取了教训
the earlier languages
因此它不仅功能更强大，也更易用
to make something that is both powerful
and easy to use
Java 和 Kotlin 有一层特殊的关系——它们彼此之间互相兼容
java and kotlin have a special
relationship since they're compatible
Java 和 Kotlin 有一层特殊的关系——它们彼此之间互相兼容
with each other
如果 Java 是今天被设计的，它就会长得像 Kotlin 那样
kotlin is what java would look like if
it was designed today
在这个教程中我会使用名叫 IntelliJ IDEA 的 IDE 来编写 Kotlin 代码
to write kotlin code i'm going to be
using a program called intellij which
你可以在互联网上免费下载它（jetbrains.com/idea/download）
you can download for free from the
internet
首先，我创建了一个名为 KotlinMinutes 的空文件
to start out with i created an empty
file called KotlinMinutes
Kotlin 文件的扩展名是 .kt
the file extension for kotlin files is dot kt
我们将在 main 这个特殊的函数中编写代码
and the code we write will be
inside this
我们将在 main 这个特殊的函数中编写代码
special function called main
关于函数，我们之后会讲更多
we'll talk more about functions later
老规矩，我们要做的第一件事就是输出「你好，世界」
in classic fashion the first thing we'll
do is print out hello world
我们在这里调用 println() 函数并在双引号中输入 「Hello World!」
so we'll use this function called
println and type in hello world in
我们在这里调用 println() 函数并在双引号中输入 「Hello World!」
double quotes
现在我们可以点击这个绿色箭头来编译并运行我们刚刚写好的代码
now we'll execute our code by hitting
this green arrow which will compile and
现在我们可以点击这个绿色箭头来编译并运行我们刚刚写好的代码
run our code
编译的意思是用你写的代码生成计算机能执行的二进制文件
compiling just means taking the symbols
and keyboards you write and turning that
编译的意思是用你写的代码生成计算机能执行的二进制文件
into something that the computer can
actually execute
你可以在弹出的运行工具窗口中看到程序的运行结果
you can see the output in this run tool
在这里它输出了「Hello World!」，符合我们的预期
window that pops up where it says hello
world as we expect
让我们从变量开始我们的 Kotlin 之旅
let's start our tour of kotlin with variables
变量是一组有名字的数据
a variable is a piece of data
为了创建一个变量，你需要为它指定一个变量名和类型
which has a name and a type
例如 string（字符串）类型，它由一串字符组成
for example strings are a
sequence of characters
所以我的名字可以用 string 类型的变量来储存
so my first name would be stored as a as
a string type
要定义一个变量，我们需要使用 val 关键字
the way we'll declare the variable is
with a special keyword called val
从它在编辑器中被标以不同的颜色你就能知道，它是一个关键字
you can tell it's a keyword since it'll
turn a different color in the editor
在 Kotlin 中，每个变量都必须属于一种类型
in kotlin every variable must have a
所以我们说 Kotlin 是静态类型语言
type that's why we say
在这个例子中，这个变量名为 firstName
kotlin is statically typed so in this
example the name of the variable is
类型为 string
firstName and the type is string
因为我们在定义变量的同时就给这个变量赋了值「Rahul」（一个字符串）
because we're setting the value of the
variable equal to Rahul right away
我们其实不需要专门把这个变量定义为 string 类型
we actually don't need to specify that
这就是 Kotlin 的实用功能之一——类型识别
this is of type string
this is a nice feature of kotlin called
这就是 Kotlin 的实用功能之一——类型识别
type inference where
如果我们赋的值类型很明确，就不需要单独地定义它了
if it's obvious what the type is we
don't need to explicitly
如果我们赋的值类型很明确，就不需要单独地定义它了
indicate it there's also an important
还有一个重要概念是只读变量和可写变量
concept of whether a variable is
read-only or
还有一个重要概念是只读变量和可写变量
readable and writable if the value of a
如果一个变量的值需要在它被初始化后被修改
variable can change
after it's initialized then we have to
我们就需要使用 var 这个关键字来定义它（而不是 val）
declare it with this var
每到假期我的体重都会增加，因为我吃了太多曲奇
keyword since my weight goes up every
holiday season because of how many
每到假期我的体重都会增加，因为我吃了太多曲奇
cookies i'm eating
我们要用 var 来定义我的体重，但是我的名字
we'll use var for that but my first name
永远不会变
will never change
所以我们要用 val 来定义
so that'll be a val there are a few
除了刚刚讲的字符串和整型外，Kotlin 还内置了几种数据类型
other built-in types in kotlin in
addition to string and integer which we
除了刚刚讲的字符串和整型外，Kotlin 还内置了几种数据类型
just saw
例如 double 是用来存储像 2.5 这样的小数的
for example double is for decimals like
2.5
而布尔类型只有两种值——真或者假
and booleans only have two values either
true
编写代码的过程中，写注释有时是很有帮助的
or false as you write more code it's
编写代码的过程中，为后人留下些备注有时是很有帮助的
sometimes helpful to leave yourself a
它可以告诉将来的你和别人你为什么这么写这段代码
note about why you wrote the code in a
certain way
这些备注就叫注释，你可以打出两个斜杠（//）来让这一行作为注释被计算机（编译器）忽略
these are called comments and you can
leave a comment by using a double slash
这些备注就叫注释，你可以打出两个斜杠（//）来让这一行作为注释被计算机（编译器）忽略
commented lines are ignored by the
说完了变量，我们来讲讲运算符
computer now that we've talked about
variables
说完了变量，我们来讲讲运算符
let's look at operators which allow us
它们允许我们对这些变量进行运算
to manipulate these variables
例如，我们可以用加号（+）来把两个字符串连成一个更长的字符串
for example we can combine two strings
into a longer string with a plus sign
这种操作被称为字符串串接
which is called concatenation here we're
在这里我们把字符串 s1 和 s2 串接的结果存储在变量 combined 中并打印了出来
printing out the value of s1 plus
s2 in this variable called combined so
所以我们运行这个程序的时候我们就会得到“call me maybe”的输出
when we run the program we get the（Carly Rae Jepsen 的一首歌）
result of call me maybe which is a
它是 "call me " 和 "maybe" 串接的结果
concatenation of call me
and maybe this is an example of a binary
这是一种二目运算符，因为它需要输入两个值
operator because it takes in two inputs
如你所料，还有几种用于数字的二目运算符
there are several different binary
operators for numbers as you might
如你所料，还有几种用于数字的二目运算符
expect
我们可以把这里的两个整数 9 和 4 相加得到和 13
with two integers here having value nine
and four we can add them together and
我们可以把这里的两个整数 9 和 4 相加得到和 13
get thirteen
我们也可以用 n1 减去 n2、乘上 n2、除以 n2
we can also subtract them multiply them
或使用百分号（%）获取 n1 除以 n2 的余数
divide them or find the remainder after
the division with this percent sign
在这里取模运算的结果会是 1
that would be 1 in this case let's talk
是时候再拓展一下字符串相关的知识了
a bit more about strings
字符串是一个字符序列
strings are a sequence of characters and
你可以用它实现很多有用的功能，例如通过下标取回字符串中特定位置的字符
there are a bunch of useful things you
can do with them for example
你可以用它实现很多有用的功能，例如通过下标取回字符串中特定位置的字符
retrieving a character in the series by
indexing into the string
Kotlin 的下标和大多数编程语言一样从 0 开始
like this in kotlin like most other
programming languages we start counting
所以第一个字符K在下标为0的位置上，第二个字符O在下标为1的位置上
at zero so the first character K
will be at position zero and the second
所以第一个字符K在下标为0的位置上，第二个字符O在下标为1的位置上
character O will be position one in the
我们可以看到KOTLIN的前两个字母被打印出来了
output we can see the first two
我们也可以用 isEmpty() 方法来检查字符出是否为空
letters of kotlin we can also check if a
string is empty using the method is
它的返回值为布尔类型，即真或假
empty which returns a boolean true or
false value
我们还可以在变量名后面加上 .length 来获取一个字符串的长度，返回值为整形
or we can get the length of a string
which is an integer by using the dot
我们还可以在变量名后面加上 .length 来获取一个字符串的长度，返回值为整形
length property
运行时我们可以得知我的字符串不为空，因为其中有字符
if we run this we can see that my string
kotlin is not empty because it has
运行时我们可以得知我的字符串不为空，因为其中有字符
characters
字符串中有 6 个字母，因此字符串的长度为 6。
and there are six characters which is
why the length is six
substring() 方法则会根据我们提供的起止下标从字符串中取出子串
another method is substring which will
extract a portion of the string between
substring() 方法则会根据我们提供的起止下标从字符串中取出子串
the start and end index that we provide
在这里 substring(2, 4) 会返回 TL
so substring with parameters 2 and 4
因为我们从下标为 2 的 T 开始
will output TL because we will start at
T
往后取两位，取到下标为 3 的 L 为止，不包括下标为 4 的 I
which is index 2 include index 3 the l
and then go up 2 but not include index 4
往后取两位，取到下标为 3 的 L 为止，不包括下标为 4 的 I
the i
当你写了更多 Kotlin 代码之后，有个实用的建议：
one really handy tip as you start
writing more kotlin is to explore
在你的变量名后面输入英文句点（.）来探索更多可用的方法
other methods available to you by
hitting the dot or period
在你的变量名后面输入英文句点（.）来探索更多可用的方法
after writing the name of your variable
你会看见一个自动完成对话框
you'll get an auto complete dialog
它会向你展示你能用这个变量做的所有操作
which shows you all the possible things
you can do with this
句号可能是 Kotlin 中最重要的符号之一
variable the period is probably one of
the most important symbols in kotlin
因为它能让我们使用这种语言的自带功能
since it allows us to use the built-in
functionality of the language
值得指出的是，你能使用的方法与你的变量类型有关
one thing worth pointing out is that the
options and methods that you get
值得指出的是，你能使用的方法与你的变量类型有关
will depend on the type of the variable
例如这个 int 类型的变量适用的方法就与 string 类型不同
for example the options here
with the integer will be different than
例如这个 int 类型的变量适用的方法就与 string 类型不同
what we had with the string
关于字符串的最后一个知识点
one last point on the topic of strings
我们常常想要在字符串中输出一个变量的值
we'll frequently want to print out the
value of a variable
这种情况下我们可以用美元符号（$）来进行字符串插值
inside a string for that we'll use the
dollar sign to do string interpolation
这里的美元符号表示我们想把这个变量名替换为这个字符串存储的值
the dollar sign means that we'll replace
the variable here
这里的美元符号表示我们想把这个变量名替换为这个字符串存储的值
with the contents of it inside the
运行程序，我们可以看到输出为
string so if we run this we can see the
「The string is KOTLIN」，因为
output is "The string is KOTLIN" because
字符串中储存的值
the value of my string
是 KOTLIN。我们可以把串插值用于
is KOTLIN we can use interpolation for
任何类型的变量
variables of any type
接下来我们来讲讲条件语句
let's move on to conditionals which are
这是一种根据条件决定是否执行特定代码的方法
a way to execute certain code depending
on a condition
if 语句是一种流控制
and if statement is an example of flow
它会判断一个表达式的值是真还是假，且仅在它为真的情况下执行一些代码
control which will evaluate whether
a statement is true or false and execute
它会判断一个表达式的值是真还是假，且仅在它为真的情况下执行一些代码
some code only if it's true
例如，我们可以在 examScore 变量大于 70 时打印一条信息
for example we can print out a message
if this
例如，我们可以在 examScore 变量大于 70 时打印一条信息
exam score variable is greater than 70.
因为变量的值 88 大于 70
because the value 88 is larger than 70
我们运行这段代码时会看到「you passed!」
when we run the code we see "you passed!"
因为 if 代码块内的语句被执行了
because we're running the code inside
the if block
这里用于判断的可以是任何返回布尔类型（真或假）的表达式
the statement we're evaluating here can
be anything with a true or false return
这里用于判断的可以是任何返回布尔类型（真或假）的表达式
value
我们可以使用 examScore 大于 70
so for example we could do exams greater
than 70
或者大于等于（>=）、小于（<）、小于等于（<=）、
greater than or equal to less than less
等于（==）、
than or equal to
不等于（!=）一个值作为条件
equal to or not equal to a value
现在我把条件改回 examScore 大于 70
i'll change this back to examScore
如果我们想在这个条件不满足的时候做些什么怎么办？
greater than 70 but what if you want to
do something if that condition fails
要做到这一点，我们需要用到 else 代码块
for that we'll use an else block and the
当这个条件为假时，在这个块里的代码会被执行
code inside of here will get run if the
condition fails
在这个例子中，这意味着 examScore
in this case that means that the examScore
小于 70，所以我们将输出
is less than 70 so we'll print out
「You failed :(」
“you failed :("
现在让我们把 examScore 的值改为 55
and now let's change the examScore to
这会让 else 块内的代码被执行
55 which is something that will trigger
这会让 else 块内的代码被执行，所以
the else block to run and so here in the
在输出中你能看到 「You failed :(」的消息
output you can see the message
我们经常需要一次性定义很多变量
"you failed :(" we often want to hold a bunch
of variables at once
instead of defining them one at a time
for that we can use collections
for example instead of having a separate
variable here
for each of my friends names we can have
one variable which is a list of strings
containing all my friends names
so now if i wanted to print out the
third element in this list we could do
that
by looking at index 2 of our names list
remember that kotlin is 0 indexed so ali
is at index 0
maya index 1 and chan at index 2. when
we run this
we do indeed see 10 in the output by
default
collections in kotlin are immutable
which means we can't add or remove
elements from the list
if we want to change the contents we
must declare the list as a mutable list
by changing the declaration now we are
able to add a fourth element
all elements in a collection must have
the same type so in this example
everything is of type string
and we could actually make that explicit
by adding this string type parameter
to the declaration if we tried adding
something else into the list we would
get a compile error for example
here we're trying to add 80 which is an
integer into the list
and if i hover over it says the integer
literal does not conform to the expected
type
string it's really common to do
something on every element
in a collection the most common way of
doing that is with a for loop
for example if we wanted to print out
each element in our list of friends
names
we'd write the for loop like this for
name in names
println name if we run this we can see
the output is the three names in the
list the way i think about this
is that in every cycle or iteration of
the for loop
the variable name will take on one
element of the list
it'll go in order so first it'll be ali
then maya and then chan
the other common use of for loops is to
do something a certain number of times
we can use for i in 1.5 to execute
something
exactly five times so if you run this we
can see that the operation that we're
doing five times
is println and we're printing out i each
time
where i will take on each of the values
1 through 5 before it exits the for loop
if we don't want to include the last
number then we can do for i in 1 until 5
and that will just print out the numbers
1 through 4.
next we'll talk about functions
functions are a way to combine chunks of
your code so we can reuse them
throughout our program
this makes our code easier to read and
think about we can create a function
with the fun keyword followed by the
function name
so in this example it's my function
followed by open and close parentheses
and then the body of the function goes
inside of these curly braces
now we can invoke our function from the
main function just by
calling it with the open and closed
parenthesis if we run this the body of
my function gets
executed so we print out hello if we
want to give this function some input we
can add the parameter name and type to
the function signature
so here we have a parameter name of name
and the type of string
in the body of the function we can treat
the parameter as a normal variable
so here we're including that input into
the print line
you'll notice back in the main function
that we now have an error when trying to
call
my function and that's because whoever
invokes this function
is responsible for passing in the
correct number and type
of parameters let's pass in the string j
for the parameter and if we run this now
we can see
hello j as the output we can also set
the visibility of functions to be
private so they can't be accessed from
other classes or files
people always ask me what kind of
private fun are you having
but that's the topic for another video
finally the concept of null is really
important in kotlin
null means having no value and if a
variable is allowed to have no value
then we need to update the type to
include a question mark
this means that the variable instagram
bio is a nullable string
so on instagram if you've written a bio
then this variable would have a string
value
but if it's not set it would be null the
important thing to remember
is that we can't call any methods on
something which is null
one way to get around this is to check
if the variable is not null
and then in the body of this if
statement we can now safely call any
method we want
in this case because we're setting
instagram bio to null
we'll fail the check on line 3 which
means when we run the program we get an
empty output
however if we update instagram bio to be
a string then we will get into the body
of the
if statement and that's how we're
printing out uppercase growth
the other way of doing this is to use a
shorthand for exactly this if
check which is the question mark dot
operator so we can say instagram bio
question mark dot to upper case and this
means we'll only call this method
on this variable or this object if it's
non-null
so if we print this out we can see that
we now get growth in uppercase
printed out twice that's pretty much the
core of kotlin
we went over variables operators strings
if statements for loops and functions
if you're interested in learning more
about all the good stuff in kotlin
i'd love if you hit the subscribe button
and like this video thanks for watching
and i'll see you in the next one